The unknown grandmother
Bunica necunoscută
Like most children of my generation, I’ve  spent my holidays in the countryside,
Ca majoritatea copiilor din generația mea, mi-am petrecut vacanțele la țară,
at my grandparents, in a village of Transylvania.
la bunicii mei, într-un sat din Transilvania.
I remember my grandmother working all day in the household with  her rough hands.
Îmi amintesc că bunica lucra toată ziua în gospodărie cu mâinile ei aspre.
Today, after forty years I open the dowry chest that I have from her and my heart fills with hope.
Astăzi, după patruzeci de ani deschid lada de zestre pe care o am de la ea și inima mi se umple de speranță.
1930 it is the year of her wedding.
1930 este anul nunții ei.
The bottom of the costume was also decorated with rich lace
Fundul costumului era, de asemenea, decorat cu dantelă bogată
In a fragment of photo I can see my grandmother in 1941.
Într-un fragment de fotografie o pot vedea pe bunica mea în 1941.
She was already wearing a Romanian blouse of married woman, sewn with black,
Purta deja o bluză românească de femeie căsătorită, cusută cu negru,
after a pattern brought from Sibiu by her brother.
după un tipar adus de la Sibiu de fratele ei.
He also brought her melted linen cloth and felt from Oradea and also special threads.
I-a adus și pânză de in topită și pâslă din Oradea și, de asemenea, fire speciale.
Late in the evening, after all the hard works in the field and the household,
Seara târziu, după toate muncile grele din câmp și din gospodărie,
after she was putting the chidren to sleep, my grandmather started to sew.
după ce a adormit copiii, bunica a început să coasă.
But my grandmother was also cultivating hemp, spinned bundles, used to spin and weave.
Dar bunica mea cultiva și cânepă, mănunchiuri toarse, obișnuia să toarnă și să țese.
She made towels, decorative napkins to be put at the icon, table cloths and bed sheets,
Ea a făcut prosoape, șervețele decorative pentru a fi puse la icoană, fețe de masă și lenjerie de pat,
everything that was necessary in a household with eight people.
tot ce era necesar într-o gospodărie cu opt persoane.
All these special things were created and worn in the old house
Toate aceste lucruri speciale au fost create și purtate în vechea casă
in which they lived until 1947.
în care au trăit până în 1947.
This video was made within the Digital Storytelling Cultural Agora@Your Library October 1st-2nd, 2015
Acest videoclip a fost realizat în cadrul Digital Storytelling par Agora Culturala 2015